<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Dr. du Moulin, containing a charitable reproof for his schismatical book entituled, A short and true account of the several advances the Church of England hath made towards Rome, &amp;c. to which are added Some seasonable words to Mr. Richard Baxter.</title>
            <author>Philotheus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48215</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12979473</idno>
  <idno type="VID">96159</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248540988</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4663</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12979473</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48215)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 719:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Dr. du Moulin, containing a charitable reproof for his schismatical book entituled, A short and true account of the several advances the Church of England hath made towards Rome, &amp;c. to which are added Some seasonable words to Mr. Richard Baxter.</title>
                  <author>Philotheus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed p. 8: Philotheus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Du Moulin, Lewis, 1606-1680. --  Short and true account of the several advances the Church of England hath made towards Rome.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  True and only way of concord.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Concord.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Schism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96159:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> du Moulin, CONTAINING A CHARITABLE REPROOF FOR HIS SCHISMATICAL BOOK ENTITULED, A Short and True Account of the Several Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances the CHURCH of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> hath made towards <hi>ROME,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>TO WHICH ARE ADDED <hi>Some Seasonable Words</hi> TO M<seg rend="sup">R.</seg> RICHARD BAXTER.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Magna est Veritas, &amp; Prevalebit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:96159:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96159:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO <hi>Doctor Du Moulin, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis comes from one that has a great Esteem of your <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> and is most heartily griev'd that a Person of such Endowments, whose Father was so Intimate a Friend of the most Renowned Bishop <hi>ANDREWS,</hi> whose Brother is at this time so Great an Ornament of our Church; I say, that such a Man should <hi>condescend</hi> to the Clamors of those <hi>Ignorant, Low-spirited</hi> People, that cry out <hi>Popery, Popery,</hi> at every thing that savours of <hi>Antiquity</hi> in the <hi>Circumstantials</hi> of Religion: though indeed <hi>Popery</hi> it self be nothing else but a <hi>Novelty,</hi> as it hath been plainly Demonstrated by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Peirce,</hi> now Dean of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> in that so much Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Sermon of his, which the <hi>Papists</hi> have so often <hi>Barkt</hi> at; but none of them could ever fix a <hi>Tooth</hi> on it. I Beseech you to Read with all Seriousness, and Deliberation the <hi>Decad of Caveats,</hi> which the same Learned, and Pious, and Truly Obedient Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath lately Publish'd.</p>
            <p>You revile the Books of <hi>Heylin, Thorndike, Jeremy Taylor,</hi> and Archbishop <hi>Bramhal</hi> (you might have said Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> &amp;c.) as being infected with the Venom of <hi>Arminianism, Pelagianism,</hi> and <hi>Socinianism,</hi> and the Maxims of Dr. <hi>Hobbes.</hi> Sir, I beseech you by the Meekness and Gentleness of our Lord Jesus Christ,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96159:3"/> that you would not be so Angry with me, as it seems you were of late with one of my Brethren for Exhorting you to Repentance. Is it one of the Reasons you Dislike our Church, that she obliges all those that undertake the care of Souls, to teach all Children as soon they are able, to learn, that it is a part of their Duty towards their Neighbour, to <hi>keep</hi> their <hi>Tongue</hi> from <hi>Evil Speaking, Lying</hi> and <hi>Slandring.</hi> But you will say, all the World knows these men were <hi>Arminians.</hi> To this I answer; 'tis true, They did Declare their Dissent from Mr. <hi>Calvins</hi> Conceits about Predestination, especially the three first: And for ever Blessed be the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> that so Learned Persons were delivered from that Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, which so many still lie under. We are not <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> but Sincere Christians, in that we Oppose <hi>Calvin</hi> in this matter. One of the Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Publisht some Latine Papers against <hi>Jansenius</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> about two years since: and finding in your Friends CELEUSMA, a most wicked slanderous Imputation of <hi>Innovation</hi> in Religion, cast upon the Author of that Excellent Book, entituled The Causes of the Decay of Christian Piety: He Printed a Brief <hi>Paraenesis</hi> to your Friend, Annext to some other Papers, and sent it to Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> together with these Papers against <hi>Jansenius</hi> &amp; <hi>Calvin.</hi> But the Messenger could never come to speak with him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at length he left a Letter for him with a Friend of his, part of which I shall here recite. <hi>The Author of this Book did desire me to deliver it into your own hand; and I have often sought to do it accordingly, but could not get an opportunity. He did further enjoin me to tell you, that if you please (or any of your Friends or Party) to controvert these points with him in the Latine Tongue; he doth hereby promise you to give you an Answer in three weeks time, to any thing whatsoever shall be written by you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of these Papers, against <hi>Jansenius,</hi> has ever had a Due Reverence for that Authority, that has enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us not to trouble the Vulgar with <hi>Subtle</hi> Disputes about Predestination, and therefore has ever been Averse, even from <hi>Writing</hi> in English on this Controversial Subject. But though he does acknowledg, that some very Good and Learned Men may Dissent from him; he is so Confident, that what he has Publisht in the above mention'd Papers, is a Truth contain'd in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> that his Life shall never be so Dear
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96159:3"/> to him, as the <hi>Vindication</hi> of it. So much for their <hi>Arminianism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Pelagianism,</hi> and <hi>Socinianism,</hi> and the Maxims of Dr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> (I suppose you mean <hi>Thomas Hobbes</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury)</hi> Believe it, I cannot apprehend, how it is possible for you to Enjoy the God of Truth in this World, or in the World to come, unless you speedily repent of this most A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Slander. To go about to confute it, would be as Absurd to one that has Read the Writings of these Great Men, as to prove that 1 &amp; 2 make 3.</p>
            <p>As for Dr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> how has he been <hi>Confounded,</hi> and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to Contempt by the most Reverend Bishop <hi>Bramhal!</hi> And yet you reckon him amongst those whose Books are infected with the Venom of the Maxims of Dr. <hi>Hobbes.</hi> Do you, and your <hi>Hot-headed Party</hi> take any heed to what you speak or write? How injurious are you to the Memory of that Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Man, Archbishop <hi>Laud,</hi> in endeavouring to Perswade the Vulgar, that he was Popishly-Affected<hi>!</hi> I say, the Vulgar: For they that Read his Incomparable Book against <hi>Fisher,</hi> will Despise the most strenuous Attempts (much more such as yours) to Violate the Honour of His Memory: Whose <hi>Blood</hi> has made such a <hi>Stain</hi> upon the Reputation of your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it shall remain throughout All Generations. In the 24th. Page of your <hi>Angry</hi> Book, your Malice reaches one of the <hi>Highest</hi> of the Friends of the Church of <hi>England</hi> that ever was, or ever can be. So Natural is it to those that <hi>Revile</hi> BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHOPS, to make as light of KINGS. How <hi>Villanous,</hi> how <hi>Traiterous</hi> is it for <hi>Private</hi> Persons to put the worst Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction upon the <hi>Intricate</hi> Actions of PRINCES! The Learned Writings of this Great KING against <hi>Popery</hi> shall ever remain as a <hi>Brand</hi> of <hi>Infamy</hi> to those <hi>Phanaticks</hi> who shall ever Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, as you have done. Can you think it possible that Our most Gracious Soveraign will ever think well of such Bitter Enemies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who have thus <hi>Slander'd</hi> His Grandfather, and <hi>Murder'd</hi> His Father, a Prince whose Clemency could never be <hi>Parallel'd</hi> but by His own? whose, Life upon the account of his Clemency, 'tis certainly the <hi>Interest</hi> of all <hi>Parties</hi> to Endeavour to Preserve.</p>
            <p>The next thing I think fit to mind you of is this; That you say, <hi>p.</hi> 31. That <hi>the most numerous Party of our Church have been these twenty years endeavouring to make their Advances towards</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96159:4"/> Rome, <hi>and have run themselves into</hi> Pelagianism <hi>and</hi> Socinianism, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Strange! that one of your years should write so <hi>Inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately!</hi> Call the <hi>Papists</hi> what you please rather than <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> or <hi>Socinians!</hi> Do they not Expresly Acknowledge the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees</hi> of those <hi>Councils</hi> which Condemned <hi>Pelagius</hi>'s his Doctrine? And does not any man that knows any thing in <hi>Religion,</hi> know this, tht The <hi>Papists</hi> are no <hi>Socinians?</hi> How Ridiculous then is this your Accusation, that they make Advances towards <hi>Rome,</hi> and run into <hi>Pelagianism</hi> and <hi>Socinianism!</hi> Will you never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham'd of such Folly? Now you fall upon Doctor <hi>Patrick,</hi> and talk your pleasure of him, and recite many of his words, wherein he Elegantly sets forth the Folly of those men, who make such ill Descriptions of the Nature of Saving Faith, that according to those Descriptions, men are apt to sooth up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in their <hi>Carnal Security;</hi> and Conceit that they have <hi>Saving Faith,</hi> though they are so grosly sinful that 'tis impossible they should suppose themselves to have a Real Propensity to <hi>Keep GODS Holy Will and Commandments, and Walk in the same all the dayes of their Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length you say, and that (in my Judgment) very Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>To be short,</hi> Doctor Patrick <hi>makes no other Account of Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Faith</hi> (I suppose you mean, of Justifying Faith) <hi>but of an Hearty Assent to the Truth of the Gospel, and an Endeavouring to live according to it.</hi> An Endavouring, to wit, a sincere and Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Endeavouring. This I know to be sound Doctrine. But however, sith you Carp at the Learned Doctor's Expressions, I shall endeavour by some other Expressions to draw off your self and others from your too high Esteem of such kind of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions of Justifying Faith, by which so many men (to my certain knowledge) have sooth'd up themselves in their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities. I shall here Transcribe some part of a Brief Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course Entituled, <hi>Justifying Faith,</hi> &amp;c. Printed for <hi>William Crooke</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alas, what Stirs, and Petulant Controversies have there been, and are still continued amongst those that joyntly Profess the</hi> Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>concerning the Nature of Faith in Christ, of the Faith of</hi> Gods Elect! <hi>A man can hardly say any thing by way of Description of it, but presently up starts one or other, with some Argument to Disprove what we say. I shall do what I can in Declaring my Sense of it, to speak Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly and unexceptionably, and therefore</hi> I <hi>shall pass by such</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96159:4"/>
               <hi>of it as I have found to have been Controverted, though</hi> I <hi>do heartily approve many of them, as Implying the same Truth, which</hi> I <hi>shall endeavour to set forth in these words: The</hi> Faith <hi>we speak of,</hi> Faith by which the Just do Live, Faith that Overcometh the World, Faith that worketh by Love, <hi>is such an ASSENT to the Truths contained in the Holy Scriptures, which includes in its Nature, the Trusting in God the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth, for Grace and for Glory, through the Merits of the Past Sufferings, and the Power and Virtue of the Present Intercession of Jesus Christ, His Only Son, Our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Grace</hi> I <hi>understand</hi> Principally <hi>All those Measures of Holiness, of Purity of Heart, of Participation of the</hi> Divine Nature, <hi>which are Attainable here upon Earth, and Secondarily whatsoever the On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wise God Judges to be the Means of attaining thereunto; By Glory I understand the Full, Perfect, Eternal Enjoyments of the Holy, Blessed, and Glorious TRINITY, in the Kingdom of Heaven. By Trusting in God for Grace and for Glory Through the</hi> Merits <hi>and</hi> Intercession <hi>of Jesus Christ, I understand a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere</hi> Absolute <hi>Expectation from God, of whatsoever He Knows to conduce to our Eternal Happiness, that is, a Perfect CONFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MITY to</hi> Our Blessed Redeemer, <hi>both in Body and Soul, Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bare Account of his Promise to Give us</hi> Freely <hi>whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we shall ask of Him in the Name of his SON, that is to say, in a Sincere</hi> Belief <hi>that the SON, Being Over All, GOD</hi> Blessed for Ever, <hi>did in time, for Us Sinful Creatures to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coucile Us to the</hi> Holy Creator <hi>of all things, take upon Him the Nature of Man,</hi> was conceived by the Holy Ghost, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> suffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> was Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Dead and Buried, he descended into Hell, the third day he rose again from the dead, he ascended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and sitteth at the right hand of God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, from thence he shall come to judge the quick and the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sincerity of this Belief consists in a true and real Bent or Intention of the Heart</hi> to Live no longer unto our selves, but unto him that died for us, and Rose again. <hi>But here it may be sai'd, why do you not mention the Pardon of our sins? Must you not trust in God for that also? I answer, God's Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of our sins, is implyed in the giving us his Grace, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us Partakers of the</hi> Divine Nature, in shedding abroad
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96159:5"/> his Love in our Hearts by the Holy Ghost: <hi>For they that are</hi> Partakers of the Divine Nature, <hi>they that Love God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, from whence necessarily flows the Loving of Every Man as themselves,</hi> They are in Christ, and Christ in them<hi>: and you know the</hi> Apostle <hi>says,</hi> There is no Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them which are in Christ Jesus, who walk not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Flesh, but after the Spirit. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Due Consideration of what has been said, this most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Truth shines forth most evidently, that we cannot Do any thing accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God, but only in the Power of the Holy, Blessed, and Glorious</hi> TRNITY: <hi>and hence it is that the Frequent Repetition of the</hi> Gloria Patri, <hi>that most Excellent</hi> Doxology, Glory be to the Father <hi>&amp;c. and the like frequent mention of the Name, and Merits of Jesus Chaist our Lord; Hence it is, I say, that these Excellent Passages in Our</hi> Liturgy, <hi>which some Naughty Men have cal'd Vain Repetitions, cannot but be exceeding pleasing, and satisfactory to all truly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Devout Souls.</hi> As <hi>for those, who are still so Mad, as to Dislike this truly</hi> CATHOLICK <hi>Doxologie, they are more fit for our</hi> Pity <hi>than our</hi> Arguments: <hi>and let that</hi> Pity <hi>ever move us to pray Our</hi> Almighty and most Merciful Father <hi>to draw them out of those</hi> Waters <hi>of Srife, those Loose, Variable,</hi> Turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Opinions, and to lead them by His Good Spirit in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant ways of</hi> Truth <hi>and</hi> Peace.</p>
            <p>As for Kneeling at the Sacrament, sith it cannot be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd that any man <hi>Receives</hi> the Holy Communion as he ought to do, unless at that Time He <hi>Solemnly Adore</hi> the Person of our Crucified LORD, how it is possible that any man that has a Sincere <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> for His <hi>Infinite Majesty,</hi> can so wrangle against that <hi>Reverent</hi> Posture at such a time, I could never apprehend. O Blessed Jesus, put an End to such Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies, we Beseech thee; and Enable Us, who Use this Humble Posture, whilst we Eat thy Flesh, and Drink thy Blood, to Work mightily upon the Hearts of our Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by the <hi>Purity</hi> of our Lives and Conversations, that they may be Fully convinc'd that we <hi>Love</hi> Thee, as Our SAVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUR, and <hi>Fear</hi> Thee too, as Our LORD and Our GOD.</p>
            <p>Your Clamor, that we have given Encouragement to the <hi>Papists,</hi> &amp;c, is so notoriously Wicked, that it needs no <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,</hi> but only a <hi>sharp Rebuke.</hi> I profess, Sir, I Pity you from the bottom of my heart: And I beseech Our Almighty and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96159:5"/> most Merciful Father to give you true Repentance, and to wash your Soul in the Blood of our Redeemer from that <hi>Foul</hi> Uncharitableness, which you so plainly discover in the Conclusion of what you call A <hi>Short and True Account,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As to the Zeal and Passion</hi> (say you) <hi>which many of the Prelatical party have testified at this time against the</hi> Papists, <hi>it must be confest they do it not without reason; for commonly the greatest Friends become irreconcileable Enemies, when those Bonds that kept them together come to be dissolv'd,</hi> Proximorum odia acerrima; <hi>when it once comes to the dividing of the spoil,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>so that the best interpretation that can be made of their present Carriage, is, that the Love they have for their Benefices and Preferments, for their Bishopricks, Deanaries and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries hath sufficiently awakened them, and sharpned their Hatred, and rais'd their Indignation against</hi> Rome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are you the man that shew'd such a Disgust against one of our Brethren, for perswading you to Repentance? Can you hope to <hi>Overcome</hi> Death, unless first you Overcome the Violence of that Disorderly Spirit, that mov'd you to pour forth such an Abundance of <hi>Slanderous Speeches?</hi> When our Fathers, and Brethren, according to their Duty have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and spoken so Vigorously and Effectually against the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> will you tell the World, they do it not out of <hi>Conscience,</hi> and the Love of the Truth, but by the Impulse of a Carnal Mind? Consider we shall give account at the Day of Judgment of every Idle Word: Ah, Sir, what account will you give of so Many Bitter, Malicious, most horrid slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Words! Why will you not receive the Instructions of those Our Reverend Fathers now Living, whom you Deservedly Commend? One of the Bishops whom your Party to my Knowledge have most <hi>Devillishly</hi> slandered, as if he Favour'd Popery, has ever Approved himself to be one of the most Strenuous Adversaries the Papists ever had; though he has not thought fit to Publish the Controversies he has had with them. And I am sure He lives so, that he must needs be a Person of a <hi>Defiled</hi> Conscience, who will not Acknowledge that Common Charity Obliges us to Believe that His <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have done Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> great wrong in Reciting those wicked Invectives against the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which we hope, he has long repented of; if he have not, I pray
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96159:6"/> God to bring him speedily to Repentance. He knows not what he Does (if he Love God sincerely in any measure, as I hope he does) in bearing such a part of the <hi>Schism</hi> of this Distracted Nation. I verily believe he cannot imagine that such a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Followers Despise the Common Prayer, as Popish, Superstitious, and I know not what, and consequently De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise the Sum and Substance of the Christian Religion Contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in those several Forms of Sacred Words; placing their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in <hi>Hearing, Remembring, Repeating,</hi> &amp;c. Various Forms of Words delivered in a Pulpit, rather than in a True and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Despising of this Present World, in Exercising Love upon all Occasions even to their Enemies, in Rejoycing in Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, taking <hi>Rational</hi> Delight, and Satisfaction even in the Greatest Objects of <hi>Sensible</hi> Anguish and Vexation, that is to say, <hi>In Righteousness, and Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghost.</hi> This I write not to Calumniate them, but upon certain Knowledge of the Gross <hi>Hypocrisie</hi> of Many that Run from our Churches to Conventicles. I Consider, whilst I am writing, that we must All appear before the Judgment Seat of Christ; And I beseech you to joyn with me in that Consideration. So Wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you all Happiness, I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant for Christ's Sake, <hi>PHILOTHEUS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96159:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Some Seasonable Words</hi> TO M<seg rend="sup">R.</seg> RICHARD BAXTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce the writing of this to Dr. <hi>du Moulin,</hi> I have seen a late Book of yours, Entituled, <hi>The True and only Way of Concord, &amp;c.</hi> I beseech you to Consider the Reflexions I shall make on some Passages of the said Book with that seriousness which you profess in those Words; <q>You and I by God's great Mercy are yet alive, and may review our Actions, before we come to the Bar of God, which is like to be speedily to me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Really, Sir, it seems to me, that notwithstanding your Old Age, and manifold Professions of Christian Gravity, you are still guilty of much <hi>Vain-Glory,</hi> particularly in your <hi>Ostentation</hi> of your skill (or rather your <hi>Reading)</hi> in <hi>Logick, Physicks,</hi> &amp;c. It being your business to describe the <hi>Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace;</hi>
               <q>Unity, say you, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. is sometimes the Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of an <hi>Universal,</hi> which is but <hi>Ens Rationis,</hi> or a <hi>General Inadaequate</hi> partial conception of an existent singular Being; and so all men are ONE, as to the Species of Humantiy; and all <hi>Living</hi> things are <hi>One</hi> in the <hi>Genus of Vitality,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But we see, say you, <hi>p.</hi> 14. in Passive Matter that the parts have a natural propensity to <hi>Union,</hi> and the <hi>aggregative</hi> incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is so strong, that thence the Learned Dr. <hi>Glisson (Lib. De Vita Naturae)</hi> copiously maintaineth that all <hi>Matter</hi> hath <hi>Life,</hi> or a Natural Vital self-moving Virtue, not as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding part, but as a formal inadaequate conception: In which though I <hi>consent not,</hi> &amp;c. You had said in <hi>p.</hi> 13. `Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any one Passive Element (Earth, Water, or Air) any where existent in an <hi>Union</hi> of its proper Atomes without a mixture of any other Element, is a thing unknown to Mortals. So it is whether there be any where existent a Body of the United Atomes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <hi>Bullatae Nugae!</hi> What's all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96159:7"/> this to the <hi>Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace? viz.</hi> that you dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent from the Learned Dr. <hi>Glisson,</hi> that such and such things are (as you conceit) Unknown to Mortals? Certainly you have been very <hi>Defective</hi> in the contemplation of the deep Sense of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Saying, <hi>KNOWLEDGE puffeth up,</hi> but <hi>Charity edifieth.</hi> No wonder that you vaunt of your dissent from Dr. <hi>Glisson,</hi> who, <hi>p.</hi> 169. are advanced to that height of Confidence as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn a <hi>General Council</hi> for their severity against the <hi>Nestorians,</hi> and other <hi>Hereticks:</hi>
               <q>If all the mischievous, unskilful, proud, wrangling, and worldly ambitious strife by which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians were divided into <hi>Nestorians, Eutychians,</hi> &amp;c. and their Anathematizers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had been turned into an united force and diligence, by Light and Love, to have converted Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, what an happy case had the World been in?</q>
               <hi>And their Anathematizers:</hi> It seems you put them all together. <q>turn them out for Wranglers; no abiding for any of them in your <hi>Holy Commonwealth.</hi>
               </q> Yea, you usurp a kind of <hi>Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> over St. <hi>CYRIL, pag.</hi> 188. and <hi>pass Sentence</hi> upon Him, as a very <hi>Faulty</hi> Person. <q>
                  <hi>Cyril</hi> so carried it by Wit and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, and the Countenance of the Court, that all went for right that he had said.</q> What's the Matter now? Are you become a <hi>Nestorian Heretick?</hi> Else, I pray, why so angry with that Glorious Instrument of the <hi>Only wise God,</hi> in <hi>Curbing</hi> the Folly and Madness of the <hi>Nestorians?</hi> But all their strife, say you, was but about Words. Shall we believe you, or St. <hi>CY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RYL,</hi> and the <hi>Major part of that Great Council?</hi> Sir, In <hi>Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of this wicked Censure of yours, and in Vindication of that Excellent Man, that most Reverend Bishop St. <hi>CYRIL,</hi> I shall here repeat what I declar'd to the World about this Matter, in another Language, about ten years since, in a Treatise Entituled, <hi>Amor Dei, Lux Animae,</hi> p. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nestorius</hi> (ut loquitur <hi>Vincentius Lyrinensis</hi> Lib. contra profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Novationes, c. 17.) <hi>dum se duas in CHRISTO substantias distinguere simulat</hi> (quas insanus Haereticus <hi>Apollinaris</hi> quasi in unam contraxit, ut idem <hi>Vincentius</hi> ibidem ostendit) <hi>duas introducit repente personas &amp; inaudito secelere duos vult esse Filios DEI, duos CHRISTOS, unum DEUM, alterum HOMINEM: <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>num qui ex Patre, alterum qui sit generatus ex Matre. Atque ideo asserit Sanctam Mariam, non Theotocon, sed Christotocon esse dicendam; quia scilicet ex ea non ille CHRISTUS, qui DEUS, sed ille qui</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96159:7"/>
               <hi>erat HOMO natus.</hi> Dogma hoc scel eratissimum, Vera ac Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va Gehennae Soboles, Fundamentum Ecclesiae manifesto diruit. Aufert illum a nobis CHRISTUM, qui <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Per DIVINAM HUMANITATEM, Lapsos HOMINES Evehit ad DEUM, Viam omnibus patefaciens <hi>in Gratiam rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undi cum Justo &amp; Irato DEO,</hi> Plena ac Perfecta <hi>Satisfactione</hi> pro omnibus HOMINUM Omnium Peccatis PATRI OMNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POTENTI exhibita per Unam Sui in Cruce <hi>aacrificati</hi> Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ut loquitur <hi>Proclus</hi> Episcopus <hi>Cyzicus</hi> in Homilia habita sedente <hi>Nestorio</hi> in magna Ecclesia <hi>Constantinopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> quam videre est apud <hi>Binium,</hi> Tom. 2.) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Certainly, Sir, you render your self a most unfit person to compose Differences amongst Christians, who endeavour thus to perswade us to condemn a <hi>General Council,</hi> even for that, wherein they were <hi>most Orthodox,</hi> and to cast a Cloud upon the Illustrious Name of so Great a Champion of the Truth. I join with you in your highest Commendations of <hi>Unity,</hi> &amp;c. But, <hi>I</hi> pray, Sir, should we not rather desire, and contend for this, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Dissenters</hi> may at length comply and submit themselves to the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Constitutions</hi> both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> than that those <hi>who have the Rule over them</hi> should abolish any of their <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Constitutions</hi> in Compliance with these <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions</hi> Real or Pretended, which they still judge to be most <hi>Peevish</hi> and <hi>Erroneous?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Beseech you, <hi>Sir,</hi> to consider what you cannot but <hi>know of</hi> the <hi>Crooked,</hi> and <hi>Perverse</hi> Conceits, and Practises, that Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands have run into that have taken a <hi>Disgust</hi> to that Form of found Words, the <hi>Liturgy of the Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which you know, most of the men you Plead for would fain have to be <hi>Abolisht,</hi> and cast out of all Churches once again, to the great Dishonour of GOD, and <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> to the World. We grant that there are in this very Kingdom a sort of People no less <hi>Angry</hi> with St <hi>Athanasius,</hi> than you are with St. <hi>Cyril,</hi> yea such as plainly deny the <hi>Deity</hi> of our Saviour. We boldly Aver that those that would lessen that <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Bishops,</hi> are <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> to the Grand Design of the Devil, and his Principal Agents to destroy those <hi>Ecclesiastical Constitutions,</hi> whereby we uphold the Solemn Profession of the <hi>Fundamental Truths</hi> pertaining to <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Godliness.</hi> I shall here repeat some words of a Letter that has been formerly sent you: And I beseech you by the <hi>Meekness and Gentleness of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ,</hi> to consider them: for I am sure that I first wrote, and do now Repeat them upon a mature Consideration, that I must shortly appear before the Judgement-Seat of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here I could run out with much</hi> Fervour <hi>of Indignation against the</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96159:8"/>
               <hi>Despisers of these Means of Grace, and strong Guards from those Accursed Errors,</hi> Socinianism, &amp;c. <hi>which whilst I liv'd in</hi> Oxford, <hi>seem'd to me to be coming in like a</hi> Mighty <hi>Torrent upon this Distracted Kingdom, whilst the frequent Professions of Belief of the TRINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY,</hi> Gloria Patri, <hi>and the</hi> Three Creeds, <hi>were cast out of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. If it be said, what Reformation have we now?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I Reply that one Reason of this Kingdoms Miscarriages, I might say, Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is, that some of those, that are sincerely Learned, and Pious, have not such an Esteem of our Liturgy, as they Ought to have; and hundreds that are thought by the Vulgar to be so, do themselves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise it, or Countenance others in so doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I shall tell you, you are very <hi>Disingenuous,</hi> in spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Persecution &amp;c.</hi> Having so long time enjoy'd so Great <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance</hi> from the Magistrate in your Open and most Notorious Violation of the Law, still in Force against <hi>Conventicles. Verbum sapienti.</hi> It is not the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Genius</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that has ever prompted any man to speak to this effect; That the most Consciencious <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> Deserve to be most <hi>Severely</hi> Punished, rather than the most <hi>Leud</hi> and <hi>Debaucht</hi> Sort of People. No, Sir, I doubt not but you well know, that the Sincere and Obedient Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> desire that no other Punishment should be inflicted on you, but what is <hi>Truly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, viz.</hi> that which is not so Heavy, as to <hi>weigh down</hi> a Mans Conscience, by any Strong and Vehement Temptation, to Do that which he still Believes to be <hi>Sinful,</hi> or so <hi>Light,</hi> that any man could be willing to incur the Danger of it, rather than Perform or Abstain from such Actions, whose Performance or Omission is such, that 'tis very possible for him to Learn that it is not any way <hi>Forbidden</hi> by the LORD Our God, who has commanded us to <hi>Submit our selves to Every Ordinance of Man for his Sake:</hi> So that nothing can take off the Obligation, which the Eternal God has lai'd on us, to be <hi>Actively</hi> Obedient to Our <hi>Superiors</hi> upon Earth; but his own <hi>Prohibition</hi> of what they Command us. This Sir, I beseech you to Consider: and I must earnestly Beg of you By all the Professions you have made of a Tender Love to the Souls of Men, that you would not <hi>Dissemble</hi> what you know of this Great Concern of the Souls of all the <hi>Non-Conformists,</hi> But endeavour still (as you once began to do) to shew them their Sins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Consider I pray you, whether your self have not perform'd many Actions, contrary to the <hi>Laws,</hi> both of Church and State, which you would not have done, if you had been perswaded that you should have been Punish'd for so doing, according to those Laws: If you have been guilty of such Actions, Consider whether you have not been very <hi>Scandalous,</hi> and an <hi>Encourager</hi> of Gross Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the Violation of that clear <hi>Apostolical Injunction: Submit your selves, &amp;c.</hi> Ah, Sir, if you will <hi>keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace;</hi> Consider the Force of these words; and do not in the least <hi>Connive</hi> at their Wickedness; who either out of a <hi>Stubborn Humour,</hi> or a loose <hi>unsetled Opinion</hi> Rush into Sin, as the Horse Rusheth into the Battle, by the most wilful Violation of <hi>Known</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96159:8"/>
               <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Constitutions, &amp;c.</hi> You say in your Pleading for our U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the <hi>Non-Conformists: Is not he a Christian, that believeth according to the sense of the Institution (of Baptism) in</hi> God <hi>the</hi> Father, Son <hi>and</hi> Holy Ghost, <hi>and by a solemn Vow and Covenant</hi> devoteth himself to him, as his God and Father, his Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and Saviour, and his Sanctifier and Comforter, and the Witness of Christ; and hereupon that hath Right to Justification, Adoption, and the heavenly Inheritance? Who is a Christian, if this be not? <hi>p.</hi> 102. doubtless such a man a is sincere Christian; But yet certainly our <hi>Superiors</hi> have sufficient grounds to exclude that man from the Holy Communion, though he makes Professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of being such a one, as you have here Describ'd, who Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse at the Receiving of the <hi>Consecrated Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> by KNEE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LING to make the most Humble Acknowledgment of his Due SUBJECTION to our <hi>Crucified</hi> LORD: I say they have sufficient grounds to Exclude him, <hi>viz.</hi> upon a Just Suspition of his <hi>Insin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity,</hi> whatever his Pretences be.</p>
            <p>I shall take the Confidence to Recite unto you the forepart of a Discourse I delivered some years since to a very Knowing Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, in the Vindication of the Orders and Constitutions of our Church. But here perhaps some will be ready to say, It seems to us very strange, that a Christian should be so zealous for such things as you were speaking of, Things which you your self confess to be <hi>Extrinsecal</hi> to Religion, that they are not of the Substance or Nature of it. To this I Answer, that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be lightly esteem'd, that is Enjoyn'd to be Observ'd, By those that <hi>have the Rule over us,</hi> in matters appertaining to Religion. This <hi>Zeal</hi> for the Observance of such Injunctions does arise in <hi>Meek</hi> and <hi>Humble</hi> Souls, from a sense both of <hi>Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Authority, Enjoyning them to be Observ'd; and this <hi>Zeal</hi> doth also Arise from a due Value, or Esteem of the Things themselves. The Force of <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Authority is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Exprest in these words, in the Epistle to <hi>Hebrews. C.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you,</hi> &amp;c. And the Power that <hi>Civil</hi> Authority has over the Conscience, that is to say, that Charge which God gives to all that Fear his Holy Name, to obey our Earthly Governours in all things, not contrary to the Commands of the God of Heaven; this I say is as plainly Exprest in the words of the Apostle, as was ever any thing Exprest in any words whatsoever. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Ye must needs be subject, not only for Wrath, but also for Conscience sake.</hi> O! then submit your selves as S. <hi>Peter</hi> Exhorts, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2. 13. <hi>to Every Ordinance of Man for the Lords sake.</hi> The extraordinary great Value or Esteem, which truly Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Devout Souls have for these Things, <hi>Abstracting</hi> from the Authority, by which they are Enjoyn'd, is grounded upon a Belief, that there is much more of <hi>Concern</hi> and <hi>Usefulness</hi> to the Publick in them, than 'tis easy for any man, According to his <hi>Private Judgment</hi> to Apprehend: And <hi>Secundarily,</hi> upon <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of this Usefulness for the improving of the Life and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of True Religion, which <hi>Experience</hi> such Souls attain unto more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96159:9"/> and more in the Conscientious Observance of the said Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Church, <hi>viz.</hi> That St. <hi>Athanasius's Creed</hi> shall be said on several Sundays, and HOLY-DAYS that the <hi>NICENE</hi> (or if you will, the <hi>Constinopolitan)</hi> CREED shall be Said Every Sunday, and Every Holy Day; And that the <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> shall be said after Every Psalm, and divers other Parts of the <hi>Liturgy.</hi> Certainly the most Sober and truly Devout Christians cannot but have a Great Zeal, and Fervent Love for those Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Forms of sound words, rejoycing exceedingly, whilst the whole Congregation gives Glory to God, in that Heavenly <hi>Dox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology: Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost,</hi> &amp;c.. Though perhaps, many of them have never heard of, <hi>Arrius, Socinus,</hi> and such like <hi>Hereticks,</hi> from whose Dangerous Temptations the Church has taken care to Defend her Children, by calling them to such Frequent <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Adherence</hi> to those <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Truths,</hi> from which these most Abominable <hi>Hereticks</hi> so subtlely Endeavour to seduce them.</p>
            <p>Here I cannot but break forth into the highest Indignation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst those <hi>Absurd</hi> and <hi>Malicious</hi> Men, who charge our Church with the Horrid Guilt of Countenancing <hi>Socinianism;</hi> whereas 'tis as clear as the Sun at Noon, that every <hi>Socinian</hi> in any of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Dominions is a <hi>Non-Conformist:</hi> And Let those other <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> who Endeavour to get that strong <hi>Fortification</hi> Against All <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> to be slighted and Demolisht, I mean Our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy;</hi> Let them, I say, Think with themselves what service they do to the DEVIL, and his Chiefest Assistants, the <hi>SOCINIANS,</hi> Whilst they Teach the People to Despise that Plain, aad most <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible Form of sound Words; how is it possible, but that they should at least <hi>Cool</hi> their Affections towards the Truths therein Contain'd? What readier way can there be to Prepare them for the Reception of the most Damnable Doctrine of the <hi>Anti-Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> than by teaching them to sleight the <hi>Common Praier,</hi> which is the very Extract and <hi>Quintessence</hi> of the <hi>Sound Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Devotion</hi> of the Antient Fathers; Those who lived Five Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years after the <hi>Sun of Righteousness</hi> had Illuminated all the Dark Corners of the Earth? Call all the Labours of the <hi>Church of God,</hi> for the Estabishment of Fundamental Points of the Christian Religiion, in Opposition to <hi>Arrius,</hi> and other <hi>Hereticks</hi> in those Days, go for nothing? Shall Our Congregations be no way Advantag'd by them? Shall the Loose <hi>Scribbles,</hi> or <hi>Extemporary Harangues</hi> of any Gifted Brother, (as they use to speak) be <hi>Prefer'd</hi> before them? <hi>Hear, O Heavens, and Hearken, O Earth!</hi> What a Generation is This! Who Pretend to Assert the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and yet sleight the <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> sleight <hi>St. Athanasius's Creed!</hi> This fort of Men you so earnestly <hi>Plead for,</hi> as if Our <hi>Superiours</hi> could not <hi>keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace,</hi> unless they will Comply with their <hi>Turbulent Humours.</hi> I wish that all Men of your <hi>Disputing</hi> Genius, would be deeply Thoughtful of that <hi>Divine</hi> Maxim, <hi>In multit udine Verborum non deerit Peccatum:</hi> And of that saying of the <hi>Royal Philosopher,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fica Teipsum.</hi> Farewel. The LORD Give you Understanding in All Things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>